--==CMCT团队 荣誉出品==--
影片压制; 如烟  字幕调校: 铭u
w
招募Q号:76846146
--==CMCT团队 荣誉出品==--
影片压制; 如烟  字幕调校: 铭u
ww
招募Q号:76846146
--==CMCT团队 荣誉出品==--
影片压制; 如烟  字幕调校: 铭u
www
招募Q号:76846146
--==CMCT团队 荣誉出品==--
影片压制; 如烟  字幕调校: 铭u
www.
招募Q号:76846146
--==CMCT团队 荣誉出品==--
影片压制; 如烟  字幕调校: 铭u
www.H
招募Q号:76846146
--==CMCT团队 荣誉出品==--
影片压制; 如烟  字幕调校: 铭u
www.HD
招募Q号:76846146
--==CMCT团队 荣誉出品==--
影片压制; 如烟  字幕调校: 铭u
www.HDc
招募Q号:76846146
--==CMCT团队 荣誉出品==--
影片压制; 如烟  字幕调校: 铭u
www.HDcm
招募Q号:76846146
--==CMCT团队 荣誉出品==--
影片压制; 如烟  字幕调校: 铭u
www.HDcmc
招募Q号:76846146
--==CMCT团队 荣誉出品==--
影片压制; 如烟  字幕调校: 铭u
www.HDcmct
招募Q号:76846146
--==CMCT团队 荣誉出品==--
影片压制; 如烟  字幕调校: 铭u
www.HDcmct.
招募Q号:76846146
--==CMCT团队 荣誉出品==--
影片压制; 如烟  字幕调校: 铭u
www.HDcmct.c
招募Q号:76846146
--==CMCT团队 荣誉出品==--
影片压制; 如烟  字幕调校: 铭u
www.HDcmct.co
招募Q号:76846146
--==CMCT团队 荣誉出品==--
影片压制; 如烟  字幕调校: 铭u
www.HDcmct.com
招募Q号:76846146
罗马帝国在全盛时期的版图
由非洲沙漠延伸至
英格兰北部边境
罗马皇帝更掌控了全世界
三分之一以上人口的生杀大权
在西元180年的冬天 马可・奥勒留皇帝(著名的哲学皇帝)
12年征战讨伐日耳曼野蛮部落的行动
即将宣告结束
只要扫平最后一处据点 罗马大军便可获得胜利
而帝国从此可以永享太平
日耳曼尼亚(今德国境内)
长官
Sir.
将军
General.
长官
Sir.
士兵们又累又饿
Lean and hungry.
- 还没有动静吗? - 完全没有
- Still nothing? - Not a sign.
- 他去了多久? - 将近两小时了
- How long has he been gone? - Nearly two hours.
他们会开战吗? 长官?
Will they fight, sir?
我们很快就会知道了
We shall know soon enough.
士兵 把投石车往前挪点
Soldier, I ordered you to move those catapults forward.
- 射程不够远 - 射程没问题
- They're out of range. - Range is good.
- 可能会误伤轻骑兵的... - 不用担心 同意吧?
- The danger to the cavalry... - Is acceptable. Agreed?
他们拒绝投降
They say no.
他们应该认命了 他们已被征服了
People should know when they're conquered.
你会吗 昆塔斯?
Would you, Quintus?
我会吗?
Would I?
- 勇气与荣耀 - 勇气与荣耀
- Strength and honor. - Strength and honor.
收到我的信号后就发动攻击
At my signal, unleash hell.
投石车准备
Load the catapults.
步兵组成进攻队形
Infantry form up for advance.
- 弓箭手准备 - 弓箭手!
- Archers ready. - Archers!
- 搭箭! - 搭箭!
- Nock! - Nock!
弟兄们!
Fratres!
- 马西墨斯! - 马西墨斯!
- Maximus! - Maximus!
三星期后 我将在田里收割庄稼
Three weeks from now, I will be harvesting my crops.
想象下你要去的地方 愿望就要实现了
Imagine where you will be, and it will be so.
保持队形 跟我冲啊
Hold the line! Stay with me!
如果你发现自己落单了
If you find yourself alone,
迎着阳光 独自驰骋在草原上时
riding in green fields with the sun on your face,
不用迷惑
do not be troubled.
那是因为你已在天堂了 你已经阵亡了
For you are in Elysium, and you're already dead!
兄弟们...
Brothers,
我们生平的事迹
what we do in life
将永远流传
echoes in eternity.
拉!
Pull!
投石车准备就绪 长官!
Cohorts ready, sir!
弓箭手 点火!
Archers, ignite!
- 点火! - 点火!
- Ignite! - Ignite!
弓箭手 拉满弓!
Archers, draw!
射!
Loose!
好了 大家开始进攻
All right, men, ready!
保持队形
Hold the line!
射!
Loose!
填装弹药!
Reload!
保持队形!
Hold the line!
- 拉弓! - 射!
- Draw! - Loose!
跟着我冲!
Stay with me!
罗马必胜!
Roma victor!
普利托里亚十四
你认为他真的快死了吗?
Do you think he's really dying?
十年来 他一直过都是这样子
He's been dying for 10 years.
如果他不是快不行了 就不会派人来召见我们了
If he werert really dying, he wouldn't have sent for us.
也许他只是想念我们呢
Maybe he just misses us.
那元老会的议员们呢? 没事他不会传唤他们的 除非
And the senators? He wouldn't have summoned them if...
安静点 康莫德斯
Peace, Commodus.
在路上两星期里
After two weeks on the road,
你老是疑神疑鬼的 烦死我了
your incessant scheming is hurting my head.
他已作了决定 他将会宣布
He's made his decision. He's going to announce it.
传位给我
He will name me.
我将要做的第一件事...
The first thing I shall do when...
就是举行大型的竞技比赛来荣耀他
Is honor him with games won'thy of His Majesty.
现在 我最想做的第一件事 就是淋个热水浴
For now, the first thing I shall do is have a hot bath.
殿下?
Your Highness?
看来我们就快到了
We seem to be almost there, sir.
- 殿下 - 皇帝在哪里?
- Sire. - Where's the Emperor?
殿下 他在前线 已经去了19天了
He's at the front, sire. They've been gone for 19 days.
伤员还在不断的运回来
The wounded are still coming in.
备马
My horse.
殿下
My lord.
给我一个吻?
Kiss?
你再次证明了你的勇猛 马西墨斯
You have proved your valor yet again, Maximus.
希望这是最后一次了
Let us hope, for the last time.
我们已经没有敌人了 陛下
There's no one left to fight, sire.
永远不能掉以轻心 敌人无处不在
There is always someone left to fight.
我该怎样奖赏罗马最伟大的将军呢?
How can I reward Rome's greatest general?
恩准我回家
Let me go home.
家
Home.
凯撒 他们向你致敬
They honor you, Caesar.
是向你致敬 马西墨斯 他们尊敬你
It's for you, Maximus. They honor you.
我错过了这次的战役了吗?
Have I missed it? Have I missed the battle?
你错过了整场战争
You have missed the war.
父亲 恭喜你
Father, congratulations.
我会献上100头公牛来庆祝你的胜利
I shall sacrifice 100 bulls to honor your triumph.
那到不必
Save the bulls.
向马西墨斯致敬吧 是他打赢了这场战役
Honor Maximus. He won the battle.
- 将军 - 陛下
- General. - Highness.
罗马向你致敬 而我以兄弟的身份拥抱你
Rome salutes you, and I embrace you as a brother.
很久没见了 老朋友
It has been too long, my old friend.
陛下
Highness.
来 父亲 让我来扶你
Here, Father. Take my arm.
我想我是时候离开了
I think it is time for me to leave.
这就是罗马的荣耀
So much for the glory of Rome.
宏伟的战役
Magnificent battle.
将军 还活着?
General. Still alive?
还活着
Still alive.
天上的诸神也有幽默感的
The gods must have a sense of humor.
- 他们一定特别照顾你 - 维勒瑞斯
- The gods must love you. - Valerius.
将军 你是要回军营呢? 还是回罗马?
Back to barracks, General? Or to Rome?
回家 我妻子孩子还有庄稼都在等着我
Home. My wife, my son, the harvest.
农夫马西墨斯 我还是无法想象你当农夫的样子
Maximus the farmer. I still have difficulty imagining that.
你知道的 泥垢要比血迹容易洗掉 昆塔斯
You know, dirt cleans off a lot easier than blood, Quintus.
- 他在这里 - 陛下
- Here he is. - Highness.
议员盖尔斯 议员佛克
Senator Gaius, Senator Falco.
当心盖尔斯 他会替你洗脑
Beware of Gaius. He'll pour a honeyed potion in your ear,
接着某天你醒来 就只会高喊"共和万岁 共和万岁"
and you'll wake up one day and all you'll say is, "Republic, republic, republic."
有何不可? 毕竟罗马创建时是共和制的
Well, why not? Rome was founded as a republic.
在共和制下 共和国是由元老会来执政的
Yes, and in a republic the senate has the power.
当然 议员盖尔斯绝不是因此才从政的
But Senator Gaius isn't influenced by that, of course.
你支持谁呢? 将军? 皇帝还是元老院?
Where do you stand, General? Emperor or Senate?
军人的职责就是
A soldier has the advantage
保家卫国上阵杀敌 议员
of being able to look his enemy in the eye, Senator.
有军队支持 你要从政易如反掌
Well, with an army behind you, you could be extremely political.
我警告了你 二位 失陪一下
I warned you. Now I shall save you. Senators.
马西墨斯
Maximus.
我将会需要你的帮助
I'm going to need good men like you.
有什么我可以效劳的 殿下?
How may I be of service, Highness?
只有你才知道该如何指挥军队
You're a man who knows what it is to command.
在你的领导下 无人不服 战无不胜
You give your orders, the orders are obeyed, and the battle is won.
但那些议员们只会争吵算计阿谀奉承还有欺骗
But these senators scheme, squabble and flatter and deceive.
马西墨斯 我们必须从政客们的手中拯救罗马
Maximus, we must save Rome from the politicians, my friend.
到时候我能期待你的帮助吗?
Can I count on you when the time comes?
殿下 只要你父亲恩准我离开 我打算立刻回家去
Highness, when your father releases me, I intend to return home.
回家? 你是应该回家看看
Home? Well, no one's earned it more.
可别耽于安逸 也许我很快就会需要你的
Don't get too comfortable. I may call on you before long.
露西拉来了 你知道吗?
Lucilla's here. Did you know?
她还没有忘记你
She's not forgotten you.
而现在 你是个英雄了
And now, you're the great man.
如果你生为男人的话
If only you had been born a man,
你会成为一位伟大的凯撒
what a Caesar you would have made.
父亲
Father.
你会很强壮
You would have been strong.
我想知道 你会很公正吗?
I wonder, would you have been just?
我不会辜负你对我的教导和期望
I would have been what you taught me to be.
旅途怎样?
How was yourjourney?
漫长 不舒服 为什么要我来?
Long. Uncomfortable. Why have I come?
我需要你的帮忙 和你弟弟有关
I need your help. With your brother.
当然
Of course.
他爱你 他一向都很爱你
He loves you. He always has.
另外
And
他现在比往常更需要你
he will need you now, more than ever.
不谈政治了
Enough of politics.
我们何不假装你是一个可爱的女儿
Let us pretend that you are a loving daughter,
而我则是个好父亲
and I am a good father.
令人愉快的假设 不是吗?
This is a pleasant fiction, isn't it?
早上好
Good morning to you.
再给我三匹马
I need three more horses.
一! 二! 三!
One! Two! Three!
四!
Four!
一! 二!
One! Two!
你召见我吗 凯撒?
You sent for me, Caesar?
- 凯撒? - 再告诉我一遍 马西墨斯
- Caesar? - Tell me again, Maximus.
我们为什么会在这里?
Why are we here?
为了罗马的荣耀 陛下
For the glory of the empire, sire.
没错
Yes.
对 我记起来了
Yes, I remember.
看到那地图了吗 马西墨斯?
Do you see that map, Maximus?
那就是我所创建的世界
That is the world which I created.
25年来...
For 25 years,
我四处征战 半生戎马 才有今天的局面
I have conquered, spilt blood, expanded the empire.
自从我成为凯撒后 据我所知只有四年没有战争
Since I became Caesar, I've known four years without war.
在20年里 只有四年的和平
Four years of peace in 20.
这一切究竟是为了什么?
And for what?
我只给大家带来了战争 仅此而已
I brought the sword. Nothing more.
凯撒 你的一生...
Caesar, your life...
求你 不要那么叫我了
Please. Please don't call me that.
过来
Come. Please.
过来坐下
Come sit.
让我们好好谈谈
Let us talk together now,
纯粹是男人之间的闲聊
very simply, as men.
说吧 马西墨斯
Well, Maximus,
说吧
talk.
我有5000个人在外面的泥浆中挨冻
Five thousand of my men are out there in the freezing mud.
其中3000人浑身是伤
Three thousand of them are bloodied and cleaved.
另外有2000人再也无法离开这里 他们都已经死了
Two thousand will never leave this place.
我绝不相信他们的牺牲毫无意义
I will not believe that they fought and died for nothing.
那你相信什么 马西墨斯?
And what would you believe?
他们为了你和罗马而战
They fought for you and for Rome.
罗马是什么 马西墨斯?
And what is Rome, Maximus?
我到过世界上别的许多地方
I've seen much of the rest of the world.
那里既冷酷又阴暗 罗马象征着光明
It is brutal and cruel and dark. Rome is the light.
但你从没去过那里
Yet you have never been there.
你没看见罗马已经变成什么样了
You have not seen what it has become.
我快要死了 马西墨斯
I am dying, Maximus.
当一个快死的时候
When a man sees his end,
他会想知道自己的一生是否有价值
he wants to know there was some purpose to his life.
人们将来会怎么评价我呢?
How will the world speak my name in years to come?
会推崇我是个哲学家?
Will I be known as the philosopher?
一名勇士?
The warrior?
还是位暴君?
The tyrant?
或是让罗马回归自我的皇帝?
Or will I be the Emperor who gave Rome back her true self?
恢复共和制的罗马是个梦想
There was once a dream that was Rome.
你只能悄悄地说
You could only whisper it.
再大声一点的话 它将会消失
Anything more than a whisper and it would vanish,
它是如此的脆弱
it was so fragile.
我担心在残酷的现实环境中 他根本无法存活下去
And I fear that it will not survive the winter.
马西墨斯
Maximus,
让我们说点悄悄话
let us whisper now,
只有我和你
together, you and I.
你有个儿子
You have a son.
说说你讲你的家庭
Tell me about your home.
我家在提基洛附近的山丘上
My house is in the hills above Trujillo.
一个非常简单的地方
A very simple place.
在阳光下的暖和的红砖屋
Pink stones that warm in the sun.
白天 菜园里飘着药草的香味
A kitchen garden that smells of herbs in the day,
到了晚上则是茉莉花的味道
jasmine in the evening.
门外有一棵高大的白杨树
Through the gate is a giant poplar.
无花果树 苹果树和梨树
Figs, apples, pears.
土壤是黑色的 比我妻子的头发还黑
The soil, Marcus, black. Black like my wife's hair.
南坡上种葡萄 北坡种着橄榄
Grapes on the south slopes, olives on the north.
野生的小马在我家附近玩耍 他们常逗我的儿子玩
Wild ponies play near my house. They tease my son.
他也想变成一匹小马
He wants to be one of them.
你上一次回家是什么时候?
When was the last time you were home?
2年又264天 还要算上今天早上
Two years, 264 days and this morning.
我羡慕你 马西墨斯 你有个幸福的家庭
I envy you, Maximus. It's a good home.
值得你为它如此奋斗
Worth fighting for
在你回家之前
There is one more duty
我希望你帮我做最后一件事
that I ask of you before you go home.
你要我做什么 凯撒?
What would you have me do, Caesar?
我要你在我死后成为罗马的保护者
I want you to become the protector of Rome after I die.
我会把政权交给你
I will empower you to one end alone,
将权力还给罗马的人民
to give power back to the people of Rome,
结束危害罗马的贪污腐败
and end the corruption that has crippled it.
你愿意接受这光荣的使命吗?
Will you accept this great honor that I have offered you?
我打心眼里...不愿意
With all my heart, no.
马西墨斯
Maximus,
这就是我一定要授权给你的原因
that is why it must be you.
但这应该是行政官或者议员的职责
But surely a prefect, a senator,
一个了解罗马 熟悉政治的人
somebody who knows the city, who understands her politics.
但你还没被罗马的政治腐蚀
But you have not been corrupted by her politics.
- 康莫德斯呢? - 康莫德斯不是正人君子
- And Commodus? - Commodus is not a moral man.
你比谁都要清楚这一点
You have known that since you were young.
康莫德斯不能统治罗马
Commodus cannot rule.
绝对不可以
He must not rule.
我要是有你这样的儿子就好了
You are the son that I should have had.
康莫德斯会接受我的决定的
Commodus will accept my decision.
他知道军队只对你效忠
He knows that you command the loyalty of the army.
我需要时间考虑
I need some time, sire.
好吧
Yes.
我希望在日落之前你能答应我的请求
By sunset, I hope you will have agreed.
现在 象儿子般拥抱我吧
Now embrace me as my son.
顺便再帮我拿条毯子来
And bring an old man another blanket.
- 我父亲现在只宠爱你 - 夫人
- My father favors you now. - My lady.
- 以前不是这样 - 很多东西都改变了
- It was not always so. - Many things change.
话是没错 但不是所有的事情
Many things. Not everything.
马西墨斯 站住
Maximus, stop.
让我看看你的脸
Let me see your face.
- 你看起来很沮丧 - 我失去了很多部下
- You seem upset. - I lost many men.
我父亲找你有什么事?
What did my father want with you?
在我回家前祝我一路顺风
To wish me well before I leave for home.
你在撒谎
You're lying.
我总能看穿你在撒谎 因为你不精于此道
I could always tell when you were lying, because you were never any good at it.
我一直都不习惯你的安慰
I never acquired your comfort with it.
没错
True.
反正你也不需要
But then you never had to.
对军人来说 生活要简单的多
Life is more simple for a soldier.
或许你觉得我很无情?
Or do you think me heartless?
我觉得你具备生存的天分
I think you have a talent for survival.
马西墨斯 停下
Maximus, stop.
再次见到我真的这么可怕吗?
Is it really so terrible seeing me again?
不 我只是厌倦了战争
No. I'm tired from battle.
看到我父亲是那么脆弱 你很心痛
It hurts you to see my father so fragile.
康莫德斯期望父亲会很快宣布他是断任者
Commodus expects that my father will announce his succession within days.
你会像追随我父亲那样对我弟弟效忠吗?
Will you serve my brother as you served his father?
我会永远对罗马效忠
I will always serve Rome.
你知道吗
Do you know,
我还是不忘替你祈祷
I still remember you in my prayers.
是的 我有祈祷
Oh, yes. I pray.
听到你丈夫去世的消息我很难过 我替他追悼
I was sad to hear of your husband's death. I mourned him.
- 谢谢你 - 我听说你有个儿子
- Thank you. - And I hear you have a son.
是 他叫卢修斯
Yes. Lucius.
他快八岁了
He'll be nearly eight years old.
我儿子也快八岁
My son is also nearly eight.
谢谢你的祈祷
I thank you for your prayers.
祖先们 我祈求你们指引我
Ancestors, I ask for your guidance.
天上的母亲 求你指示我未来的方向
Blessed Mother, come to me with the gods' desire for my future.
天上的父亲 求您保佑我的妻儿
Blessed Father, watch over my wife and son with a ready sword.
请转告他们 我只是为再次拥抱他们而活
Whisper to them, I live only to hold them again.
祖先们 我荣耀你们
Ancestors, I honor you,
并将谨遵祖训 有尊严的活下去
and will try to live with the dignity you have taught me.
西斯洛
Cicero.
主人
Sir.
我不觉得履行义务很困难吗?
Do you ever find it hard to do your duty?
有时我做我想做事
Sometimes I do what I want to do.
其余的时间我做我应该做的事
The rest of the time, I do what I have to.
也许我们还是不能回家去
We may not be able to go home, after all.
你准备好对罗马履行你的职责了吗?
Are you ready to do your duty for Rome?
是的 父亲
Yes, Father.
你不会成为皇帝
You will not be emperor.
哪位年长的智者会取代我的地位?
Which wiser, older man is to take my place?
我会将政权移交给马西墨斯
My powers will pass to Maximus,
直到确认
to hold in trust,
元老院准备好再次治理罗马
until the Senate is ready to rule once more.
罗马会再度成为共和国
Rome is to be a republic again.
- 马西墨斯 - 对
- Maximus. - Yes.
我的决定使你失望了吗?
My decision disappoints you?
你曾写信给我
You wrote to me once,
上面列举了四种主要的美德
listing the four chief virtues.
智慧...
Wisdom,
公正...
justice,
坚毅...
fortitude,
和自律
and temperance.
读完信后我就明白自己一种都不具备
As I read the list, I knew I had none of them.
但我有其他的美德 父亲
But I have other virtues, Father.
野心
Ambition.
当它驱使我们做的更优秀的时候 这也是一种美德
That can be a virtue when it drives us to excel.
智谋 勇气
Resourcefulness, courage.
也许和行军打仗无关 但...勇气也有很多种的
Perhaps not on the battlefield, but there are many forms of courage.
对家庭的全心全意的奉献...
Devotion to my family,
还有对你的爱
to you.
但你完全不欣赏我所有的优点
But none of my virtues were on your list.
就像你根本不希望有我这样的儿子
Even then it was as if you didn't want me for your son.
康莫德斯
Commodus,
你想的太多了
you go too far.
我向天上的诸神祈求...
I searched the faces of the gods
让我能够讨你欢心 让你能够以我为荣
for ways to please you, to make you proud.
只要一句赞美
One kind word,
或是一个拥抱...
one full hug,
把我紧紧的抱在你怀里
where you pressed me to your chest and held me tight,
都会象慈蔼的阳光温暖我的心
would have been like the sun on my heart for 1, 000 years.
为什么你如此讨厌我?
What is it in me you hate so much?
康莫德斯
Commodus.
我不敢有任何奢求...
All I've ever wanted
只求能符合你的期望 凯撒
was to live up to you, Caesar.
- 父亲 - 康莫德斯...
- Father. - Commodus,
养子不教...
your faults as a son
实为我作为父亲的过错啊
is my failure as a father.
过来
Come.
父亲
Father.
为了让你能爱我...
I would butcher the whole world,
即使血洗天下我也在所不惜!
if you would only have loved me!
马西墨斯 皇帝有急事要找你
Maximus, the Emperor needs you. It's urgent.
和我一起哀悼 兄弟
Lament with me, brother.
我们伟大的父亲去世了
Our great father is dead.
他怎样死的?
How did he die?
医生们说是呼吸衰竭
The surgeons say there was no pain.
他在睡梦中安详的走了
His breath gave out as he slept.
父亲
Father.
新皇帝需要你的忠诚 马西墨斯
Your emperor asks for your loyalty, Maximus.
宣誓效忠于我
Take my hand.
我只给你一次机会
I only offer it once.
昆塔斯
Quintus.
凯撒万岁
Hail, Caesar.
我要去见议员们 我需要他们的意见
I must talk to the senators. I need their counsel.
- 去叫醒盖尔斯和佛克 - 盖尔斯和佛克
- Wake Gaius and Falco. - Gaius and Falco.
- 我的剑 - 剑
- Sword. - Sword.
马西墨斯 请三思而行 你的举动太过轻率
Maximus, please be careful. That was not prudent.
轻率? 皇帝是被人谋杀的
Prudent? The Emperor has been slain.
皇帝是自然死亡
The emperor died of natural causes.
- 你为什么全副武装 昆塔斯? - 守卫!
- Why are you armed, Quintus? - Guards!
请不要反抗 马西墨斯请不要反抗 马西墨斯
Please don't fight, Maximus.
我很抱歉 是凯撒下的命令
I'm sorry. Caesar has spoken.
骑马西行...
Ride until dawn,
在拂晓前处死他
and then execute him.
昆塔斯 看着我 看着我!
Quintus, look at me. Look at me!
答应我 你会好好照顾我的家人
Promise me that you will look after my family.
你的家人会在黄泉路上与你相会的
Your family will meet you in the afterlife.
跪下
Kneel.
天上的父亲 请保护我的妻子和儿子
Blessed Father, watch over my wife and son.
转告他们我只为再次拥抱他们而活
Whisper to them that I live only to hold them again.
至少让我死的痛快点
At least give me a clean death.
一个军人式的死亡
A soldier's death.
有时候 霜会把刀刃粘住的
The frost, sometimes it makes the blade stick.
禁卫兵!
Praetorian!
你上次回家是什么时候?
When was the last time you were home?
2年264天 再算上今天早晨
Two years, 264 days and this morning.
天上的父亲 求您保佑我的妻儿
Blessed Father, watch over my wife and son with a ready sword.
我会尝试像你教导一样有尊严地生活
I will try to live with the dignity you have taught me.
告诉他们 我生存是为了再次拥抱他们
Whisper to them, I live only to hold them again.
世间名利 于我皆如粪土
...with a ready sword, for all else is dust and air.
告诉他们 我生存是为了再次拥抱他们
Whisper to them, I live only to hold them again.
世间名利 于我皆如粪土
For all else is dust and air.
爸爸!
Papa!
你不能死
Don't die.
你们会再见面的
You'll meet them again.
现在还不是时候
Not yet.
不! 他们能洁净你的伤口 等着瞧吧
No. They will clean it. Wait and see.
千万别死
Don't die.
他们会拿你喂狮子的
They'll feed you to the lions.
它们比我们更值钱
They are won'th more than we are.
好点吧?
Better now?
看见了吗? 伤口已经消炎了
Clean. You see?
祖卡巴 罗马领地
普罗西莫! 我的老朋友
Proximo! My old friend.
每次只要你来这里 那天就一定会是个好日子
Every day is a great day when you are here,
今天...是你最幸运的一天
but today is your most fortunate day.
你卖给我的那些长颈鹿...根本不会交配
Those giraffes you sold me, they won't mate.
他们只会走来走去吃东西却不交配
Theyjust walk around eating and not mating.
你卖给我的长颈鹿是同性恋
You sold me queer giraffes.
- 快把钱退还给我 - 不可能
- I want my money back. - Not a chance.
- 我给你好价钱 - 什么货?
- I do special price for you. - On what?
你看过我的新货了吗? 去看看吧
Have you seen my new stock? Come and see them.
他们有谁懂得搏斗吗? 我最近会有一场比赛
Do any of them fight? I've got a match coming up.
有些人善于搏斗 其他人只会去送死
Some are good for fighting, others for dying.
我想两种人你都需要
You need both, I think.
站起来!
Get up.
你以前是干什么的?
What's your trade?
我是猎人
I was a hunter.
不 我是在迦太基附近的盐矿场把他买来的
No, I bought him from a salt mine in Can'thage.
坐下
Sit down.
军团的标记
Mark of the legion.
- 逃兵 - 也许是吧 有谁在乎呢?
- Deserter. - Maybe so, but who cares?
他是个西班牙人
He's a Spaniard.
我要六个人... 给你1000
I'll take six. For 1, 000.
一千? 那个努米底亚人就值2000了
1, 000? The Numidian alone is won'th 2, 000.
这群奴隶根本不中用
These slaves are rotten.
人不可貌相 不 不 不 不 等等
It all adds to the flavor. No, no, no, wait! Wait!
等一下! 价钱好商量
I can negotiate.
我给你2000...另外给4000买那些野兽
I'll give you 2, 000, and 4, 000 for the beasts.
既然是老朋友 一共给你5000
That's 5, 000 for an old friend.
快一点! 还有多久才能回到家?
Come on! How long does it take to get into my own house?
我是普罗西莫!
I am Proximo.
接下来的几天 将是你们悲惨的日子...
I shall be closer to you for the next few days,
结束前的最后的几天 我会和你们异常的亲近
which will be the last of your miserable lives,
胜过把你们带到这世界来的该死的母亲!
than that bitch of a mother that brought you screaming into this world.
我不是花钱买你们来做伴的!
I did not pay good money for you for your company.
我出钱是为了从你们的死亡中获利
I paid it so that I could profit from your death.
你们的人生开始时 有母亲在旁边
And as your mother was there at your beginning,
结束时 我会在你们的身旁
so I shall be there at your end.
等到死亡的命运降临时
And when you die, and die you shall,
你们将因人们的欢呼而升华
your transition shall be to the sound of...
角斗士们
Gladiators,
我向你们致敬
I salute you.
红色
Red.
黄色
Yellow.
很好
Good.
红色
- Red. - Red.
西班牙人!
Spaniard.
到此为止!
That's enough for the moment!
他迟早得认命的
His time will come.
下一个!
Next.
西班牙佬
Spaniard,
你为什么不还手?
why don't you fight?
我们必须要搏斗
We all have to fight.
我决不搏斗
Well, I don't fight.
我不应在这里 我是书吏 我负责记录...
I shouldn't be here, I'm a scribe, I write down words,
我会说七种语言
and speak seven languages.
那好
Good.
明天你可用七种语言尖叫
Tomorrow, you can scream in seven languages.
或许书吏是例外 可以赢取自由
Perhaps the scribe will be the one who wins his freedom.
自由?
Freedom?
我需要做什么?
What do I have to do?
你进竞技场 杀了我
You go in the arena and you kill me.
还有他...
And him,
和这努米底亚人...
and the Numidian,
和这逃兵
and the deserter.
再多100个人
And 100 more.
直到你杀了所有斗士 你便自由了
And when there's no more to fight, you're free.
我做不到
I can't do that.
做不到?
No?
但我做得到
But I can.
那是你信奉的神吗?
Is that the sign of your gods?
这样做他们不会生气吗?
Will that not anger them?
神眷顾你
The gods favor you.
红色是天神的颜色
Red is the gods' color.
今天你会需要他们帮助
You will need their help today.
普罗西莫!
Proximo!
一直是日耳曼领导的?
Still leading with the German?
观众喜欢野蛮人
The crowd love a barbarian.
而且他令我富有
Besides that, he's making me rich.
那努米底亚人搏斗过没有?
Has that Numidian fought before?
没有 第一次
No, first time.
那个 是奴隶 士兵?
And that one, laborer, soldier?
他是西班牙人
He's a Spaniard.
在场上像个废人一样
He might as well be a eunuch for what he brings to the ring.
五百元买努米底亚人 和西班牙人那队会过关
500 sestertii, the Numidian and Spaniard team makes it through.
一千元 如果努米底亚人独自过关
And 1, 000, that the Numidian makes it through alone.
你要我买自己的人输?
Are you asking me to bet against my own man?
那是不道德的
It's unethical.
如果我加到二千元呢?
What if I make it 2, 000?
你们当中有些人不愿意上场搏斗
Some of you are thinking you won't fight,
有些觉得你不能搏斗
some that you can't fight.
他们都喜欢唱高调 除非真正轮到自己出场
They all say that until they're out there.
你们听
Listen.
- 杀! 杀! 杀! - 杀! 杀! 杀!
- Kill! Kill! Kill! - Kill! Kill! Kill!
把刀用力刺进别人的身体里
Thrust this into another mars flesh,
观众会为此而向你喝彩 崇拜你
and they will applaud and love you for that.
而你...
And you,
你也会开始为了喝彩声...
you may begin to love them
而爱上他们
for that.
最终 我们都会化为一堆枯骨
Ultimately, we're all dead men.
可悲的是 我们无权选择命运 但...
Sadly, we cannot choose how,
有权决定如何面对死亡...
but we can decide how we meet that end,
惟有如此 才能作为人
in order that we are remembered
被人们追忆
as men.
快!
Come on!
左边的 拿盾牌!
On the left, draw your shields!
右边的 拿剑!
On the right, draw your swords!
- 杀! 杀! - 杀! 杀!
- Kill! Kill! Kill! - Kill! Kill! Kill!
两人一组 红色和黄色一起
Pair them up, red with yellow.
下一个!
Next!
打!
Move!
夺权者!
Usurper!
- 滚开! - 我们不要你统治 康莫德斯!
- Go away! - You'll never rule us, Commodus!
他象个凯旋的英雄般回到罗马 但他到底征服了什么呢?
He enters Rome like a conquering hero. But what has he conquered?
给他点时间 格瑞克斯 他还年轻
Give him time, Gracchus. He's young.
我相信他可以做的很好
I think he could do very well.
为罗马还是为你?
For Rome, or for you?
卢修斯 去欢迎你的母亲 她会很高兴的
Go to your mother, Lucius. It's what she'd like.
- 卢修斯! - 妈妈!
- Lucius! - Mother!
向你致敬 凯撒
Hail, Caesar.
议员们
Senators.
罗马欢迎她的新皇帝
Rome greets her new emperor.
你忠心的臣子们向你表示欢迎 陛下
Your loyal subjects bid you welcome, Highness.
谢谢你 佛克
Thank you, Falco.
说到忠心的子民 我相信他们并不太昂贵
And for the loyal subjects, I trust they werert too expensive.
- 凯撒 - 格瑞克斯
- Caesar. - Gracchus.
罗马为你的归来而欢呼 凯撒
All Rome rejoices in your return, Caesar.
有许多政务等你来处理
But there are many matters that require your attention.
请肃静! 肃静!
To order, please. To order.
凯撒 为了请你指引
For your guidance, Caesar,
凯撒 元老院已经拟订一系列的议程 好方便陛下过目...
the Senate has prepared a series of protocols
开始解决城市里的众多问题
to begin addressing the many problems in the city,
首先是希腊区的基础卫生设备...
beginning with basic sanitation for the Greek Quarter,
设法消灭该区正在蔓延的瘟疫
to combat the plague which is already springing up there.
所以 如果凯撒...
So, if Caesar...
你难道还不明白 格瑞克斯?
Don't you see, Gracchus?
这才是问题的重点 不是吗?
That's the very problem, isn't it?
我父亲花费毕生的时间...
My father spent all his time at study,
研读书本中的知识和哲学
at books of learning and philosophy.
他的晚年尽在阅读元老院的卷轴中度过
He spent his twilight hours reading scrolls from the Senate.
然而自始至终 他却忽略了人民...
And all the while, the people were forgotten.
但元老会就代表人民 陛下
But the senate is the people, sire,
由人民中选出议员 为人民说话
chosen from among the people to speak for the people.
我怀疑民众是否象你一样丰衣足食 格瑞克斯
I doubt many of the people eat so well as you do, Gracchus.
或是像盖尔斯一样妻妾成群
Or have such splendid mistresses, Gaius.
我自认了解我的子民
I think I understand my own people.
那么 根据您个人的多方面的经验...
Then perhaps Caesar will be so good as to teach us,
陛下或许会不吝赐教
out of his own extensive experience.
我认为是爱
I call it love.
我会爱民如子 因为他们都是我的子民
I am their father. The people are my children.
我会将他们紧紧的拥抱在我的胸前
And I shall hold them to my bosom and embrace them tightly.
陛下 你曾拥抱过身染瘟疫的人吗?
Have you ever embraced someone dying of plague, sire?
没有 但如果你再打断我的话
No, but if you interrupt me again,
我保证你一定会的
I assure you that you shall.
议员 我弟弟非常疲倦
Senator, my brother is very tired.
把议程给我 凯撒应该照人民的意愿行事
Leave your list with me. Caesar shall do all that Rome requires.
夫人 你总是让人不能不服
My lady, as always, your lightest touch commands obedience.
他们凭什么对我说教?
Who are they to lecture me?
康莫德斯 元老院自有它的用处
Commodus, the Senate has its uses.
什么用处? 他们只会耍嘴皮子
What uses? All they do is talk.
根本就只需要...你和我...
It should be just you and me and Rome.
千万不可以这么想! 元老院自建国之初就存在着
Don't even think it. There's always been a Senate.
罗马已经变了
Rome has changed.
只要有一个皇帝...就可以治理帝国了
It takes an emperor to rule an empire.
当然 让人民继续拥有...
Of course, but leave the people their...
幻想
Illusions?
传统
Traditions.
我父亲对野蛮人发动战争...
My father's war against the barbarians.
他自己也承认那毫无意义 但是人民敬爱他
He said it himself, it achieved nothing. But the people loved him.
人民总是喜欢胜利的感觉的
The people always love victories.
为什么? 他们并没有目睹战争的残酷
Why? They didn't see the battles.
日耳曼人和他们毫不相关
What do they care about Germania?
他们只关心罗马的富强
They care about the greatness of Rome.
"罗马的富强"
"The greatness of Rome."
那到底是什么呢?
Well, what is that?
是一种理念... 富强
It's an idea. Greatness.
- 富强是一种憧憬 - 没错 一个憧憬
- Greatness is a vision. - Exactly. A vision.
你还不明白吗 露西拉?
Do you not see, Lucilla?
我会给人民一个罗马的新憧憬 他们会为此而敬爱我
I will give the people a vision of Rome, and they'll love me for it.
他们很快就会忘掉那几个爱说教的老头
And they'll soon forget the tedious sermonizing of a few dry old men.
我会给罗马人民一个前所未有的憧憬
I will give the people the greatest vision of their lives.
斗士 - 暴力
酒 酒 酒! 红酒白酒任君畅饮!
White and red wine for your drinking pleasure!
竞技
Games.
整整150天的竞技活动
One hundred and fifty days of games.
他比我想象中的要聪明
He's cleverer than I thought.
聪明 要不是因为害怕他的禁卫队...
Clever. The whole of Rome would be laughing at him,
全罗马的人都会嘲笑他的
if they werert so afraid of his Praetorians.
害怕和好奇...强而有力的组合
Fear and wonder. A powerful combination.
你真的认为民众会被他的手段所欺骗?
You really think the people are going to be seduced by that?
我觉得他了解罗马的本质 罗马是由一群乌合之众组成的
I think he knows what Rome is. Rome is the mob.
变魔术给他们看 就可以转移他们的注意力
Conjure magic for them, and they'll be distracted.
夺去他们的自由 他们还是会继续哄堂大笑
Take away their freedom, and still they'll roar.
维系着罗马命脉的...并不是元老院里的大理石
The beating heart of Rome is not the marble of the Senate.
而是竞技场内的沙地
It's the sand of the Colosseum.
他会把死亡带给人民
He'll bring them death,
而人民会为此而敬爱他
and they will love him for it.
你只需杀杀杀
All you do is kill, kill, kill.
观众不是要屠夫 他们要英雄
The crowd don't want a butcher, they want a hero.
我们要他们不断回来看
We want them to keep coming back.
所以不要只顾把他们斩杀 记着你是要娱乐观众
So don't just hack them to pieces, remember you are an entertainer.
西班牙人
Spaniard.
快去娱乐他们!
So entertain!
你们还不满意吗? 你们还不满意吗?
Are you not entertained? Are you not entertained?
你们不正是为此而来这里的吗?
Is this not why you're here?
西班牙人!
Spaniard! Spaniard! Spaniard!
- 西班牙人! 西班牙人! 西班牙人! - 西班牙人! 西班牙人! 西班牙人!
- Spaniard! Spaniard! Spaniard! - Spaniard! Spaniard! Spaniard!
你想要些什么?
What do you want?
女孩?
Girl?
男孩?
Boy?
- 你找我有事? - 是的
- You sent for me. - Yes, I did.
西班牙人 你的确很棒 但你还不是最厉害的
You're good, Spaniard, but you're not that good.
你可以变的更优秀
You could be magnificent.
我杀人是因为你要我这么做 这样就够了
I'm required to kill, so I kill. That is enough.
也许在乡下小地方是够了 但在罗马却行不通
That's enough for the provinces, but not for Rome.
那年轻皇帝安排了一系列表演...
The young emperor has arranged a series of spectacles
来纪念他的父亲 马可・奥勒留
to commemorate his father, Marcus Aurelius.
我觉得很好笑...
I find that amusing,
因为正是马可・奥勒留...
since it was Marcus Aurelius, the wise,
博学 无所不知的马可・奥勒留...禁止了搏斗竞技活动
the all-knowing Marcus Aurelius, that closed us down.
在这个跳蚤为患的村庄...
So finally, after five years of scratching a living
生活了五年以后
in flea-infested villages,
我们终于要回到属于我们的地方...
we're finally going back to where we belong.
罗马竞技场
The Colosseum.
你应该去看看竞技场 西班牙人
You should see the Colosseum, Spaniard.
五万罗马观众...
Fifty thousand Romans,
注视着你斗剑时的一举一动
watching every movement of your sword,
期待你挥出致命的一击
willing you to make that killer blow.
在你挥剑之前的寂静...和那之后的骚动
The silence before you strike and the noise afterwards.
喧闹声不断的提高...
It rises. It rises up,
就象...一场暴风雨...
like a storm.
而你自己就是雷神
As if you were the thunder god himself.
- 你曾是个角斗士? - 对 我是
- You were a gladiator? - Yes, I was.
你赢得了你的自由?
You won your freedom?
很久以前 皇帝...
A long time ago, the Emperor
送给我一把剑
presented me with a rudius.
那只是一把木剑
It's just a wooden sword.
你得到自由的象征
The symbol of your freedom.
他用木剑点了点我的肩 我便获得了自由
He touched me on the shoulder, and I was free.
你认识马可・奥勒留?
You knew Marcus Aurelius?
我没说我认识他 我说他曾经碰过我的肩膀
I did not say I knew him. I said he touched me on the shoulder once.
你问我到底想要什么
You asked me what I want.
我也希望站在皇帝面前...
I, too, want to stand in front of the Emperor,
就像你一样
as you did.
那你就得听我的 向我学习
Then listen to me. Learn from me.
我并不是最棒的 因为我杀人太快了
I wasrt the best because I killed quickly.
我之所以是最棒的 是因为民众崇拜我
I was the best because the crowd loved me.
赢取观众的心 你就能赢得自由
Win the crowd, and you'll win your freedom.
我会赢得观众的心
I will win the crowd.
我将让他们看见从未见过的东西!
I will give them something they've never seen before.
那么 西班牙人 我们一起去罗马
So, Spaniard, we shall go to Rome together
展开一趟血腥的冒险!
and have bloody adventures.
观众会让我们的荷包撑满...
And the great whore will suckle us
开心的笑不出来
until we are fat and happy and can suckle no more.
然后...
And then,
杀了足够多的人后
when enough men have died,
也许你就可以得到你的自由
perhaps you will have your freedom.
接着 这个给你
Here. Use this.
在远处的某个地方...有我的祖国
It's somewhere out there, my country.
我的家
My home.
我的妻子正在准备食物
My wife is preparing food.
我的女儿从河边打水回来
My daughters carry water from the river.
我还能再见到他们吗?
Will I ever see them again?
我想没机会了
I think, no.
你相信死后能再见到他们吗?
Do you believe you'll see them again when you die?
我相信
I think so.
但是 我很快就会死了
But then, I will die soon.
他们会再活很多年
They will not die for many years.
我得等他们
I'll have to wait.
但是你愿意...等
But you would? Wait?
当然
Of course.
你知道的
You see,
我的妻儿...
my wife and my son
已经在等着我了
are already waiting for me.
你会再见到他们的 只是时候未到
You'll meet them again. But not yet.
时候未到
Not yet.
- 除非... - 时候未到
- Unless... - Not yet.
时候未到
Not yet.
他在那里
There he is.
出来!
Out.
快出来!
Move, go, out!
老朋友 真高兴又看见你
Good to see you again, old friend.
带给我财富
Bring me fortune.
你以前看见过这么壮观的建筑吗?
Have you ever seen anything like that before?
我不知道他们是如何办到的
I didn't know men could build such things.
赢得观众的心
Win the crowd.
快进去! 走
Get inside. Move.
进去
Inside.
他睡的好香因为他备受宠爱
He sleeps so well because he's loved.
走吧 弟弟 已经很晚了
Come, brother. It's late.
我将使罗马成为当代的奇迹
I will make Rome the wonder of the ages.
那是格瑞克斯和他的朋友所不明白的
That is what Gracchus and his friends don't understand.
我的欲望在脑海中起伏 让我头痛欲裂
All my desires are splitting my head to pieces.
康莫德斯 喝了这苏打水
Commodus, drink this tonic.
我看时机已经成熟
I think the time is almost right.
我可以在悼念父亲的庆典上...
I could announce the dissolution of the Senate
宣布解散元老院
at the celebration to honor our father.
你认为我该这么做吗?
Do you think I should?
人民能接受吗?
Are the people ready?
我想你现在需要休息
I think you need your rest now.
你会不会留下来陪我?
Will you stay with me?
弟弟 你还是怕黑吗?
Still afraid of the dark, brother?
是的
Still.
永远都怕
Always.
- 今晚留下来陪我? - 你知道那不可能
- Stay with me tonight. - You know I won't.
那就吻我一下
Then kiss me.
晚安 弟弟
Sleep, brother.
又聋又哑的仆人...
Having servants who are deaf and mute
至少让我活得久一点
at least ensures I live a little longer.
他们在拘捕学者
They're arresting scholars now.
任何敢表达意见的 甚至包括作家和史学家
Anyone who dare speak out. Even satirists and chroniclers.
还有数学家
And mathematicians.
全部送到斗兽场
And all to feed the arena.
国会没有通过戒严法
The Senate did not approve martial law.
这全是禁卫军的恐怖势力
This reign of terror is entirely the Praetorians.
我入黑后不敢外出
I'm afraid to go out after dark.
你更应担心日间的出行
You should be more afraid of your activities during the day.
国会中布满他的线眼 由那好色的科高领导的
The Senate is full of his spies, led by that whore master, Falco.
究竟他在想什么? 那是最令我困惑的
But what is in his mind? That's what I trouble myself with.
他整天只顾...
He spends all his days singularly obsessed,
筹划你父亲的纪念庆典
planning the festival to honor your father.
他连政府最基本的工作也忽略
He neglects even the most fundamental task of government.
他到底在计划什么?
So just what is he planning?
用什么来支付?
And what pays for it?
每天这些竞技支出庞大 但我们没加新税项
These daily games are costing a fortune, yet we have no new taxes.
未来
The future.
用未来支付
The future pays for it.
他已开始卖贮备的谷物
He's started selling the grain reserves.
不是吧
This can't be true.
他在卖罗马贮备的谷物
He's selling Rome's reserves of grain.
人民在两年后便会捱饿
The people will be starving in two years.
希望他们享受这游戏...
I hope they're enjoying the games,
那些竞技不久他们便会因此而灭亡
because soon enough they'll be dead because of them.
- 罗马人要知道真相 - 怎样?
- Rome must know this. - And how?
他打算解散国会
He's going to dissolve the Senate.
谁会及时告诉他们? 你 格瑞克斯?
And who will tell them before it's too late? You, Gracchus?
你 盖尔斯
You, Gaius.
你会否在国会上发表演说
Will you make a speech on the floor of the Senate,
指责我哥哥?
denouncing my brother?
然后看着你全家被推进斗兽场?
And then see your family in the Colosseum?
谁敢?
Who'd dare?
我每天都活在恐惧中...
I have been living in a prison of fear every day,
因为我儿子是皇位继承人
because my son is heir to the throne.
他一定要死
He must die.
但昆塔斯和禁卫军会夺去控制权
Quintus and the Praetorians would simply seize control for themselves.
不 把领导者杀了就不会失去控制权
No. Cut off the head and the snake cannot strike.
露西娜 盖尔斯说得对
Lucilla, Gaius is right.
不能压制禁卫军的话 我们不会成功
Until we can neutralize the Praetorians, we can achieve nothing.
那我们坐以待毙?
So we do nothing?
不 我们在暗中计划
No, child. We keep our counsel.
我们准备
We prepare.
人民支持他 我们的声音便没有力量
As long as the people support him, we are voices without steel.
我们是空气
We are air.
但每天他都在竖敌
But with every day that passes, he makes enemies.
终有一天 他的敌人会多过朋友
One day, he'll have more enemies than friends.
那就是我们行动的时候
And on that day, we will act.
那时我们便反击
Then we will strike.
在那刻来临前...
But until then,
我们是听话的
we are docile.
我们是服从的
We are obedient.
而我们亦是不忠的
And we are treacherous.
快!
Come on!
好了 够了
All right, that's enough.
皇帝想看搏斗
The Emperor wants battles,
但我不想牺牲最好的斗士
and I don't want to sacrifice my best fighters.
观众想看竞技 所以皇帝就举办大型的竞技搏斗
The crowd wants battles, so the Emperor gives them battles.
- 你的人将参加迦太基的战役 - 迦太基的大屠杀
- You get the battle of Can'thage. - Massacre of Can'thage.
你为什么不把监狱里的
Well, why don't you go down to the prison,
乞丐小偷都找来?
round up all the beggars and thieves?
我们早就这么做了
We've done that.
如果你想要我牺牲
If you want to give away the best gladiators
全帝国最棒的角斗士
in the whole of the empire,
就得给我双倍的钱
then I want double the rates.
我们要么按照合约给钱 要么就取消合约
You'll get your contract rates, or you'll get your contract canceled.
你不高兴吗?
You don't like it?
那就滚回你的老家去
Then you can crawl back down that shit hole that you came from.
等等 卡西亚斯!
Cassius, please. You can free us.
你就是外号"西班牙人"的角斗士吗?
Gladiator, are you the one they call the Spaniard?
是的
Yes.
他们都说你力大无穷
They said you were a giant.
他们说你单手就能捏碎大人的头
They said you could crush a mars skull with one hand.
大人的? 不可能
A mars? No.
小孩的也许可以
A boy's.
- 西班牙有良种马吗? - 有最优秀的马
- Do they have good horses in Spain? - Some of the best.
这是银子 这是黑点
This is Argento and this is Scan'to.
他们是我的马
They were my horses.
可是被别人抢走了
They were taken from me.
我很喜欢你 西班牙人 我会替你加油的
I like you, Spaniard. I shall cheer for you.
- 他们准你看竞技比赛? - 我舅舅说这会使我变得勇敢
- They let you watch the games? - My uncle says it makes me strong.
- 那你父亲怎样说? - 我父亲死了
- And what does your father say? - My father is dead.
卢修斯少爷 该走了
Master Lucius, it is time.
我得走了
I have to go.
你叫卢修斯?
Your name is Lucius?
卢修斯维勒斯 为了纪念我父亲
Lucius Verus, after my father.
往下放!
Lower!
- 哥地亚斯! - 是?
- Claudius! - Yes?
- 克劳迪亚斯! 还要更多的盾牌! - 好的 长官
- More shields! - All right.
当皇上进场时 举起你们的武器向他致敬
When the Emperor enters, raise your weapons, salute him,
然后齐声向他问候!
and then speak together.
面对着皇帝 不可以背对着他!
Face the Emperor and don't turn your back on him.
去吧! 为荣誉而战!
Go, and die with honor.
欢迎伟大的凯撒!
Hail, mighty Caesar!
- 凯撒万岁! 凯撒万岁! - 凯撒万岁! 凯撒万岁!
- Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! - Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! Caesar!
- 角斗士们向您致敬! - 角斗士们向您致敬!
- We who are about to die salute you! - We who are about to die salute you!
今天...
On this day
我们把战场移到神圣的古代...
we reach back to hallowed antiquity
呈现在各位面前的是...
to bring you a re-creation of the second fall
迦太基沦亡的历史战役!
of mighty Can'thage!
在荒芜的扎马平原上...
On the barren plain of Zama
汉尼拔将军的...
there stood the invincible armies
不可战胜的野蛮人军队正严阵以待
of the barbarian Hannibal.
来自所有残暴民族的...
Ferocious mercenaries and warriors
佣兵和战士们...
from all brute nations,
毫不留情的破坏
bent on merciless destruction,
征服
conquest.
你们的皇帝很荣幸的为大家介绍...
Your emperor is pleased to give you
野蛮的异帮人!
the barbarian horde!
有人在军队里服役过吗?
Anyone here been in the army?
有 我曾在凡度巴纳和你一起服役
Yes. I served with you at Vindobona.
你可以帮我忙
You can help me.
不管从铁门后出现的是什么
Whatever comes out of these gates,
我们只有同心协力才会有较大的胜算
we've got a better chance of survival ifwe work together.
你明白吗?
Do you understand?
只有团结一致 我们才能活命
Lfwe stay together, we survive.
我很荣幸为你们介绍...
The Emperor is pleased to bring you the legionnaires
非洲的西比欧军团
of Scipio Africanus!
奋战到底!
To the death!
- 杀! 杀! 杀! - 杀! 杀! 杀!
- Kill! Kill! Kill! Kill! - Kill! Kill! Kill! Kill!
大家靠拢!
Stay close.
集合起来!
Come together!
纵队交错排列!
Stay close. Staggered columns!
你没机会了!
You don't have a chance.
固定盾牌! 紧密衔接!
Lock your shields. Stay as one.
稳住!
Hold!
稳住! 盾牌衔接起来!
Hold! As one!
做得好
Well done.
稳住! 下面!
Hold. Down low!
好!
Yes!
贺格!
Hagen!
一队去移战车! 一队...跟我来!
This column to the chariot! This column stay with me!
快点!
Quickly!
- 去前面! - 快!
- Get out there. - Hurry!
马西墨斯!
Maximus!
单排队形! 排成一排!
Single column! Single column!
我们赢了!
We win!
我对历史不太清楚 卡西亚斯
My history's a little hazy, Cassius,
不过应该是野蛮人打输了迦太基战役吧?
but shouldn't the barbarians lose the battle of Can'thage?
是的 陛下
Yes, sire.
请见谅 陛下
Forgive me, sire.
没关系 我喜欢惊喜
No, I rather enjoy surprises.
他是谁?
Who is he?
他们叫他做西班牙人 陛下
They call him the Spaniard, sire.
我想见见他
I think I'll meet him.
是 陛下
Yes, sire.
为野蛮人欢呼!
Hail to the barbarians!
前进! 严密戒备!
Forward! Arms at ready!
放下武器!
Drop your weapons.
皇帝要见你 角斗士
Gladiator, the Emperor has asked for you.
我随时听候差遣
I am at the Emperor's service.
起身 起身
Rise. Rise.
西班牙人 你果然名不虚传
Your fame is well deserved, Spaniard.
我相信其他的角斗士都不是你的对手
I don't think there's ever been a gladiator to match you.
这位年轻人坚持你是赫克托转世
As for this young man, he insists you are Hector reborn.
还是你是大力神的化身?
Or was it Hercules?
你为何不表明身份 告诉大家你的真名?
Why doesn't the hero reveal himself and tell us all your real name?
你总有名字吧?
You do have a name.
"角斗士"就是我的名字
My name is Gladiator.
你竟敢背对着我? 奴隶!
How dare you show your back to me? Slave!
脱掉头盔 告诉我你的名字
You will remove your helmet and tell me your name.
我叫马西墨斯德西斯梅里丢斯
My name is Maximus Decimus Meridius,
北方军队的指挥官
commander of the armies of the north,
菲力克斯军团的将军
general of the Felix Legions,
真正的皇帝马可・奥勒留忠心的仆人
loyal servant to the true emperor, Marcus Aurelius,
儿子被人谋杀
father to a murdered son,
妻子遭人杀害...
husband to a murdered wife,
不管今生或来世 我定会为他们复仇
and I will have my vengeance, in this life or the next.
卫兵!
Arms!
活! 活! 活! 活! 活! 活!
Live! Live! Live! Live!
- 活 活 活 - 活 活 活
- Live! Live! Live! Live! - Live! Live! Live! Live!
卫兵 退下!
Arms, at rest!
- 马西墨斯! 马西墨斯! - 马西墨斯! 马西墨斯!
- Maximus! Maximus! Maximus! - Maximus! Maximus! Maximus!
父亲
Father.
他怎么还活着?
Why is he still alive?
我不知道
I don't know.
他应该早就死了
He shouldn't be alive.
实在让人烦恼
It vexes me.
我非常生气
I'm terribly vexed.
我只是做了不得不做的事
I did what I had to do.
要是按照父亲的意愿 罗马早就解体了
If Father had had his way, the empire would have been torn apart.
你明白的 是吗?
You do see that.
是的
Yes.
你看到他的时候有何感觉?
What did you feel when you saw him?
没有任何感觉
I felt nothing.
看来他伤得你很深 对不对?
He wounded you deeply, didn't he?
我伤害他更深
No more than I wounded him.
在日耳曼的时候他们说谎
They lied to me in Germania.
他们告诉我他已经死了
They told me he was dead.
他们骗我 即是不尊重我
If they lie to me, they don't respect me.
既然如此 他们又怎么可能爱我?
If they don't respect me, how can they ever love me?
那么你必须让军团了解...
Then you must let the legions know
他们的背叛行为一定会受到惩罚
their treachery will not go unpunished.
可怜的姐姐
Poor sister.
我绝对不想与你为敌
I wouldn't want to be your enemy.
你打算怎么做?
What will you do?
出来!
This way.
贵妇人付高价是为了让英勇的角斗士取悦她
Rich matrons pay well to be pleasured by the bravest champions.
我知道你弟弟会派刺客来
I knew your brother would send assassins.
但我没想到他会派最好的来
I didn't realize he would send his best.
马西墨斯 他毫不知情
Maximus, he doesn't know.
我的家人被钉在十字架上活活烧死
My family was burnt and crucified while they were still alive.
- 我真的不知情... - 别对我撒谎!
- I knew nothing... - Don't lie to me!
我为他们哭泣
I wept for them.
就像你为你父亲哭泣?
As you wept for your father? As you wept for your father?
自从我父亲去世后 我便生活在恐惧之中
I have been living in a prison of fear since that day.
因为害怕自己的弟弟而无法哀悼自己的父亲
To be unable to mourn your father for fear of your brother.
因为自己的儿子也是王位继承人
To live in terror every moment of every day,
我时时刻刻都生活在恐惧之中
because your son is heir to the throne.
我有哭过
I have wept.
我儿子是无辜的
My son was innocent.
我儿子也是
So is mine.
难道非得用我儿子的命来换取你的信任?
Must my son die, too, before you'll trust me?
我是否信任你又有何区别?
What does it matter if I trust you or not?
你难道不明白? 神已经宽恕你了
The gods have spared you. Don't you understand?
今天我看见了比罗马皇帝还要有权力的奴隶
Today I saw a slave become more powerful than the emperor of Rome.
诸神已经宽恕我了?
The gods have spared me?
因为他们的怜悯 我才有娱乐观众的力量!
I am at their mercy, with the power only to amuse a mob.
那就是力量
That is power.
观众代表着罗马
The mob is Rome.
康莫德斯控制了他们就等于掌控了一切
And while Commodus controls them, he controls everything.
听我说
Listen to me.
元老院的大多数人都是我弟弟的敌人
My brother has enemies, most of all in the Senate.
只是当人民都支持他的时候:
But while the people follow him,
没有人敢和他正面冲突 除了你
no one would dare stand up to him until you.
他们反对他 却什么事都不做
They oppose him, yet they do nothing.
有些政治家为罗马奉献出全部的心力
There are some politicians who have dedicated their lives to Rome.
他们有个领袖
One man above all.
如果我出面安排 你愿意和他见面吗?
If I can arrange it, will you meet him?
你到底明不明白?
Do you not understand?
我只是个奴隶 随时随地都有可能丧命
I may die in this cell tonight, or in the arena tomorrow. I am a slave!
我又能改变些什么呢?
What possible difference can I make?
这个人有和你一样的目的
This man wants what you want.
那就让他去杀了康莫德斯!
Then have him kill Commodus!
我曾经认识一个人...
I knew a man once,
一个高尚的人
a noble man.
他不但有原则...而且还敬爱我的父亲
A man of principle who loved my father,
我的父亲也爱他
and my father loved him.
这个人为罗马贡献良多
This man served Rome well.
那人已经死了
That man is gone.
你弟弟干的很成功
Your brother did his work well.
让我帮你
Let me help you.
对 你能帮我
Yes, you can help me.
忘了我们曾经相识...再也不要来这里看我
Forget you ever knew me, never come here again.
守卫 这位夫人要离开了
Guard! The lady is finished with me.
你叫什么名字?
What's your name?
朱利安克拉苏
Julian Crassus.
名字?
Name?
马可斯 陛下
Marcus, sire.
跟我父亲同名
My father's name.
他们在发现马西墨斯逃走时
They must have known of Maximus' escape,
一定可以找到他们四个的尸体
when they found the bodies of the four men.
他们以为是野蛮人突袭
They thought it was a barbarian raid.
他们是好人 陛下 他们忠于皇上
These are good men, sire. Loyal to the Emperor.
搭箭!
Load your arrows!
准备放箭!
Prepare to fire!
又或者是你知道...
Then perhaps it was you who knew,
而不告诉我
and never told me.
- 我并不知道 - 你不知道?
- I didn't know. - You didn't know?
但将军永远有控制权
But a general is always in control.
永远是命令者 不是吗?
Always in command, isn't he?
是的 凯撒
Yes, Caesar.
那下命令吧 快说
Then give the command. Say it.
放箭
Fire.
马西墨斯
Maximus.
你指挥过军团? 你打过很多胜仗?
You commanded legions? You had many victories?
- 是的 - 在日耳曼?
- Yes. - In Germania?
在很多国家
In many countries.
将军
General.
你已经出名了
You have a great name.
在杀你之前他得先羞辱你的名声
He must kill your name before he kills you.
没错
Yes, at the far end.
- 盖尔斯议员 - 你好
- Senator Gaius. - Hello.
格瑞克斯议员
Senator Gracchus.
很难得看见你出现在这种龙蛇混杂的地方
Don't often see you enjoying the pleasures of the vulgar crowd.
我不会假装和人民打成一片
I don't pretend to be a man of the people, Senator,
但我会做个为人民说话的议员
but I do try to be a man for the people.
- 凯撒! 凯撒! 凯撒! 凯撒! - 凯撒! 凯撒! 凯撒! 凯撒!
- Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! - Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! Caesar!
罗马的人民!
People of Rome!
今天是安提俄克战役的第四天
On the fourth day ofAntioch,
同时也是竞技庆典的第64天
we can celebrate the 64th day of the games.
在他的仁慈下
And in his majestic charity,
皇帝决定赐予罗马人民...
the Emperor has deigned this day to favor the people of Rome
一场历史性的决战
with an historical final match.
在退休五年后...重回竞技场
Returning to the Colosseum today, after five years in retirement,
凯撒很高兴为大家请到...
Caesar is pleased to bring you
罗马历史上...
the only undefeated champion
唯一的不败冠军...
in Roman history,
来自高卢的传奇的底格里斯!
the legendary Tigris of Gaul!
他太清楚该如何操纵观众
He knows too well how to manipulate the mob.
马可・奥勒留的梦想是建立一个全新的罗马 普罗西莫
Marcus Aurelius had a dream that was Rome, Proximo.
但新罗马不应该是这样的!
This is not it. This is not it!
马可・奥勒留已经死了 马西墨斯
Marcus Aurelius is dead, Maximus.
我们只是凡夫俗子 一切终归尘土
We mortals are but shadows and dust.
一切终归尘土 马西墨斯
Shadows and dust, Maximus!
让我们隆重介绍...
Representing the training lyceum ofAntonius Proximo,
代表普罗西莫训练会馆的...
Caesar is proud to give you
马西墨斯!
Aelius Maximus!
他们把他当成自己人 敞开双臂欢迎他
They embrace him like he's one of their own.
观众是很善变的 弟弟 不出一个月就会忘记他的
The mob is fickle, brother. He'll be forgotten in a month.
错了 用不了那么久
No, much sooner than that.
一切都安排好了
It's been arranged.
角斗士向你致敬
We who are about to die salute you.
我们支持你 马西墨斯!
We're with you, Maximus!
打败他!
Fight on, finish it!
用力拉!
Pull, pull!
放开! 放开!
Loose! Loose!
- 杀了他! - 杀!
- Gut him! - Kill!
- 杀! 杀! 杀! 杀! - 杀! 杀! 杀! 杀!
- Kill! Kill! Kill! Kill! - Kill! Kill! Kill! Kill!
- 杀! - 杀!
- Kill! - Kill!
仁慈的马西墨斯!
Maximus the Merciful!
- 马西墨斯! 马西墨斯! 马西墨斯! - 马西墨斯! 马西墨斯! 马西墨斯!
- Maximus! Maximus! Maximus! - Maximus! Maximus! Maximus!
卫兵 前进 攻击队形!
Forward, arms at ready!
我该拿你怎么办?
What am I going to do with you?
为什么你...不去死
You simply won't die.
我们之间的差异真有这么大吗?
Are we so different, you and I?
必要时你也杀人...就象我一样
You take life when you have to, as I do.
只剩下一个人我非杀不可 然后我的责任就完成了
I have only one more life to take. Then it is done.
那现在就动手啊
Then take it now.
他们告诉我你儿子...
They tell me your son
在被钉上十字架的时候...象女孩子一样在尖叫
squealed like a girl when they nailed him to the cross.
还有你妻子...
And your wife
在被他们蹂躏的时候...
moaned like a whore
象妓女一样在呻吟...
when they ravaged her again and again
一次又一次...呻吟着
and again.
你呼风唤雨的日子很快就要结束了
The time for honoring yourself will soon be at an end,
陛下
Highness.
将军!
General! General!
- 将军! - 西斯洛!
- General! - Cicero!
- 将军! - 军队在哪里扎营?
- General! - Where are you camped?
在奥斯亚
Ostia.
- 我们爱你 马西墨斯! - 赞美胜利者!
- We love you, Maximus! - Praise the victor!
告诉大家我还活着 来找我
Tell the men their general lives. Find me.
- 快走! - 来找我!
- Move along! - Find me!
他们可以听到你的祈祷吗?
Can they hear you?
- 谁? - 你在黄泉的家人
- Who? - Your family, in the afterlife.
- 会的 - 你跟他们说什么?
- Yes. - What do you say to them?
对我的儿子
To my boy,
我告诉他我们很快就能见面了
I tell him I will see him again soon,
骑马的时候记得脚跟要压低点
and to keep his heels down when he's riding his horse.
对我妻子...
To my wife,
那不关你的事
that is not your business.
现在观众反而敬爱马西墨斯的仁慈
And now they love Maximus for his mercy.
因此我更不能杀他 不然就会显得我更残暴
So I can'tjust kill him, or it makes me even more unmerciful.
这整件事简直就象场恶梦
The whole thing is like some great nightmare.
他是在公然向你挑战
He is defying you.
他每一次的胜利都是种反抗的举动
His every victory is an act of defiance.
观众和元老院议员们都看到了
The mob sees this, and so do the Senate.
只要他存在一天 他们就会越来越大胆
Every day he lives, they grow bolder.
- 杀了他 - 不行
- Kill him. - No.
我不会帮他成为烈士
I will not make a martyr of him.
我今天去国会...
When I went to the Senate today,
特意告诉他们 我用了谷物贮备来支付竞技赛
I purposefully told them about using the grain reserves to pay for the games.
你记得发生什么事吗?
And did you note what happened?
- 没什么 - 对 什么都没发生
- Nothing. - Exactly. Nothing.
一句抗议都没有
Not a single word of protest.
连傲慢的格瑞克斯议员也没出声
Even the insolent Senator Gracchus was silent as a mouse.
为什么?
Why?
我听说有一种海蛇
I have been told of a certain sea snake
用非常特别的方法来诱捕猎物
which has a very unusual method of attracting its prey.
它会假装受伤 躺在海底
It will lie at the bottom of the ocean as ifwounded.
接着它的敌人会渐渐的靠近
Then its enemies will approach,
它会继续躺着不动
and yet it will lie quite still.
接着敌人会开始慢慢的咬它
And then its enemies will take little bites of it,
但它还是...一动不动
and yet it remains still.
那么
So,
我们要不动声色...
we will lie still,
耐心等待我们的敌人上钩
and let our enemies come to us and nibble.
让所有的议员也自投罗网
Have every senator followed.
西斯洛 我的老朋友
Cicero, my old friend.
我以为再也见不到你了
I thought perhaps I'd seen you for the last time.
- 我以为你死了 - 差不多
- I thought you were dead. - Close.
军团驻扎在奥斯亚有多久了?
How long have the men been in Ostia?
整个冬季
All winter.
- 他们的状况如何? ? - 整天吃饱了 无所事事
- And how do they look? - Fat and bored.
- 指挥官是谁? - 从罗马来的白痴
- Who's in command? - Some fool from Rome.
他们最快要什么时候才能准备好?
How soon do you think they could be ready to fight?
为了你 明天
For you, tomorrow.
有件事我需要你帮忙
I need you to do something for me.
各位 快来看
Come, see, witness.
如果你没去竞技场的话 你能在这里看见当时的情景
If you haven't been in the arena, you can see the show here.
马西墨斯快要打败我们的皇帝康莫德斯了 我们该怎么办?
Giant Maximus is defeating our emperor, Commodus.
他藐视每一个人
What are we to do? He's just defying everyone,
我们该怎么办?
by doing this to him, they do...
啊! 我的天啊!
My goodness!
- 他赢了! - 让路!
- He got him, he's defeated. - Give way!
公主陛下? 我在凡度巴纳侍奉过你父亲
My lady? I served your father at Vindobona.
- 退后 - 我的夫人
- Back. - My lady.
我在凡度巴纳服侍过你父亲
I served your father at Vindobona.
退后!
Back!
我也服侍过马西墨斯将军 我现在还为他服务
And I served General Maximus. I serve him still.
停下来
Stop. Stop.
停!
Stop!
退下
Stand back.
将军让我带个口信 他愿意见你说的政治家
The general sends word, he will meet your politician.
- 士兵 奖赏你的忠诚 - 谢谢 夫人
- For your loyalty, soldier. - Thank you, my lady.
出去吧
Leave us.
格瑞克斯议员
Senator Gracchus.
将军
General.
我希望今天我来这里能够...
I hope my coming here today is evidence enough
使你信任我
that you can trust me.
- 元老院和你的立场一致? - 元老院?
- The Senate is with you? - The Senate?
是的 我能代表他们
Yes. I can speak for them.
你能帮我获得自由偷偷把我运出罗马吗?
You can buy my freedom and smuggle me out of Rome?
你打算干什么?
To what end?
把我送到城外去
Get me outside the city walls.
准备好马匹让我去奥斯亚 我的军队在那里扎营
Have fresh horses ready to take me to Ostia. My army is encamped there.
我会在第二天傍晚率领五千名士兵回来
By nightfall of the second day, I shall return at the head of 5, 000 men.
但军团的新指挥官
But the legions all have new commanders,
全都效忠于康莫德斯
loyal to Commodus.
只要我的部下看到我还活你就知道他们效忠谁了
Let my men see me alive, and you shall see where their loyalties lie.
简直太疯狂了
This is madness.
百年来罗马军队从未进入过首都
No Roman army has entered the capital in 100 years.
我不愿意引狼入室!
I will not trade one dictatorship for another!
议员 已经没时间商量权宜办法了
The time for half measures and talk is over, Senator.
在你光荣的政变之后又将如何?
And after your glorious coup, what then?
你会带着五千名士兵离开罗马?
You'll take your 5, 000 warriors and leave?
我会离开
I will leave.
士兵们会留下来保护你们
The soldiers will stay for your protection,
受元老院的指挥
under the command of the Senate.
换言之
So,
一旦罗马被你控制以后...你会将它交还给人民?
once all of Rome is yours, you'll just give it back to the people?
告诉我原因
Tell me why.
因为那是某人临死前最后的期望
Because that was the last wish of a dying man.
我会杀了康莫德斯
I will kill Commodus.
罗马的命运就交给你了
The fate of Rome I leave to you.
马可・奥勒留信任你
Marcus Aurelius trusted you.
他的女儿信任你
His daughter trusts you.
我也会信任你
I will trust you.
但我们时间紧迫
But we have little time.
给我两天时间...
Give me two days,
我会想办法使你获得自由
and I will buy your freedom.
而你...
And you,
你千万要活下去
you stay alive,
否则我就死定了
or I'll be dead.
我们得走了
Now we must go.
他会在等你 站在斗兽场脚下
He'll be waiting for you. Stand at the foot of the colossus.
他会找到你
He'll find you.
不可能成功的
It won't work.
皇帝对一切都了如指掌
The Emperor knows too much.
对我来说...
And as for me,
形势越来越危险了
it's becoming dangerous.
我回来后会酬谢你的
You'll be paid on my return.
我向你保证
I give you my word.
保证? 你不回来的话怎么办呢
Your word? What if you don't return?
你还记得信任别人的感觉吗 普罗西莫?
Do you remember what it was to have trust, Proximo?
信任?
Trust?
有谁值得我信任?
Who am I to trust?
- 我会杀死康莫德斯 - 对我有什么好处?
- I will kill Commodus. - Why would I want that?
他给我带来财富
He makes me rich.
我知道你是个信守承诺的人 将军
I know that you are a man of your word, General.
我也知道你愿意为荣誉而死
I know that you would die for honor.
你愿意为罗马而牺牲
You would die for Rome.
愿意为祖先的名誉而死
You would die for the memory of your ancestors.
但我 换个角度说...
But I, on the other hand,
我不过是个表演艺人
I'm an entertainer.
守卫!
Guard!
他杀了还你自由的那个人
He killed the man who set you free.
大人 是禁卫军
Praetorians, master.
停!
Halt!
你去哪里了?
Where have you been?
我派人去找你
I sent for you.
弟弟 别疑神疑鬼了
Please, brother.
什么事让你烦心?
What's troubling you?
格瑞克斯是不是有了新爱人?
Does Gracchus have a new lover?
我不知道
I don't know.
我以为你见过他
I thought you'd seen him.
他象伤寒一样影响着每个人
He infects everyone like a putrid fever.
为罗马着想 必须要牺牲元老院
For the health of Rome, the Senate must be bled.
他也不能幸免
And he will bleed, too.
时机成熟了
Very soon.
不要选在今晚
But not tonight.
还记得父亲曾说过的话吗?
Do you remember what our father said once?
"一场梦...
"It's a dream,
生活就是...
"a frightful dream,
一场噩梦"
"life is."
你觉得他说的对吗?
Do you think that's true?
我不知道
I don't know.
我认为是真的
I think it is.
而我只能和你分享
And I have only you to share it with.
张开嘴
Open your mouth.
你知道我爱你
You know I love you.
我也爱你
And I love you.
出去 滚出去!
Out. Get out!
快点!
Move!
恭喜你 将军
Congratulations, General.
你的朋友很擅于说服别人
You've got very persuasive friends.
我弟弟已经逮捕了格瑞克斯
My brother has had Gracchus arrested.
我们不能再等下去了 今晚一定得离开
We daren't wait any longer. We must leave tonight.
普罗西莫半夜会来把你带到大门口
Proximo will come at midnight and take you to the gate.
你的仆人 西斯洛 会带着马在那边等你
Your servant, Cicero, will be waiting there with horses.
- 你一个人安排这一切的吗? - 是
- You have done all this? - Yes.
你太冒险了
You risk too much.
我有太多的债要还
I have much to pay for.
你并没有亏欠任何人
You have nothing to pay for.
你爱你的儿子 为了他 你变得十分坚强
You love your son. You're strong for him.
我已经厌倦了
I am tired of being strong.
我弟弟憎恨全世界 尤其是你
My brother hates all the world, and you most of all.
- 因为你父亲选了我 - 不
- Because your father chose me. - No.
因为我父亲爱你
Because my father loved you.
而我也爱你
And because I loved you.
很久以前的事了
A long time ago.
我变了很多吗?
Was I very different then?
你以前比较爱笑
You laughed more.
我一直都觉得很寂寞
I have felt alone all my life,
除了跟你一起时
except with you.
我要走了
I must go.
是的
Yes.
那里
There.
我赢了
And I got you.
现在玩士兵打仗不会晚了点吗?
Isn't it late to be playing legionnaire?
我不是士兵
I'm not a legionnaire.
- 不是士兵? - 我是角斗士
- Not a legionnaire? - I'm a gladiator.
角斗士?
A gladiator?
角斗士只在竞技场里打斗
Gladiators only fight in the games.
难道你不想像凯撒朱利叶...那样当一名出色的罗马战士?
Wouldrt you rather be a great Roman warrior like Julius Caesar?
我是马西墨斯 罗马的救世主!
I'm Maximus, the savior of Rome!
罗马的救世主?
The savior of Rome?
是谁说的?
And who said that?
卢修斯在哪里?
Where's Lucius?
他和皇帝在一起 夫人
He's with the Emperor, my lady.
- 她不可能那样做 - 不 是真的
- She couldn't. - Yes, she did.
她在篮中拿出来...
She took it from a basket,
她从篮子里拿出来 把它放在胸口 就在她心脏的正上方
and pressed it to her breast, right here above her heart.
- 它咬在她的胸口上? - 是的
- It bit her in the breast? - Yes.
你知道吗? 卢修斯 有时候那些皇室的小姐们...
You see, Lucius, sometimes royal ladies
为了爱可以做出一些非常奇怪的事来
behave very strangely and do very odd things in the name of love.
- 我觉得这样做很愚蠢 - 我也这么想
- I think it's silly. - So do I.
我也这么想
So do I.
姐姐 过来加入我们
Sister, join us.
我在念故事给卢修斯听
I've been reading to dear Lucius.
- 我也在读 - 没错
- I've been reading, too. - Yes.
他是个非常机灵的小男孩 总有一天他会成为了不起的皇帝的
He's a very clever little boy. He'll make a grand emperor one day.
我们在读伟大的安东尼
We've been reading about the great Mark Antony,
和他在埃及的冒险
and his adventures in Egypt.
还有皇后用蛇自杀的故事
And the queen killed herself with a snake.
我还没告诉你发生在我们祖先身上的故事
And just wait until you hear what happened to our ancestors.
如果你很乖的话
If you're very good,
明晚我会给你讲克劳迪亚斯皇帝的故事
tomorrow night, I'll tell you the story of Emperor Claudius.
他身边最亲近的人...
He was betrayed
背叛了他
by those closest to him.
他的亲人
By his own blood.
他们在黑暗的角落里商议...
They whispered in dark corners
并且在半夜偷偷出去...
and went out late at night,
共同密谋...
and conspired, and conspired.
但皇帝知道他们在策划阴谋
But the Emperor Claudius knew that they were up to something.
他知道象小蜜蜂一样忙碌
He knew they were busy little bees.
有天晚上 他和其中一人谈话...
And one night he sat down with one of them,
他看着她...
and he looked at her,
然后说...
and he said,
"告诉我你们的计划...
"Tell me what you've been doing,
忙碌的小蜜蜂
"busy little bee.
不然我会杀死你最亲的人...
"Or I shall strike down those dearest to you.
你会看到我身上沾满他们的鲜血"
"You shall watch as I bathe in their blood."
而皇帝的心都碎了
And the Emperor was heartbroken.
小蜜蜂对他的伤害
The little bee had wounded him more deeply
比任何人都要深
than anyone else could ever have done.
卢修斯 你认为接下来会发生什么事?
What do you think happened then, Lucius?
我不知道 舅舅
I don't know, Uncle.
小蜜蜂告诉了他所有的事
The little bee told him everything.
开闸 皇上有令!
Open, in the name of the Emperor!
普罗西莫!
Proximo!
开门 我们是奉皇帝的命令来的!
Open the gates, in the name of the Emperor!
普罗西莫!
Proximo!
奉皇帝的命令 开门!
Open the gates!
快开门 普罗西莫!
Open the gates, Proximo.
老头 你想找死吗?
Do you want to die, old man?
拿去
Here.
一切准备好了
Everything is prepared.
看来你赢得你的自由了
It seems you have won your freedom.
普罗西莫 当个好人是否会替你惹上麻烦
Proximo, are you in danger of becoming a good man?
- 裘巴 - 反抗皇帝的人都得死!
- Juba. - All enemies of the Emperor die!
开门! 皇帝的命令!
Open the gates!
用力拉!
Pull!
冲! 两队人去左边!
Move! Form a column on the left!
我只需要机会脱身 千万别做无谓的牺牲
I only need moments, so do not be careless with your lives.
不想被卷入这事的 就回到囚室里去
If you don't want any part of this, go back to your cells.
我们会留在这里帮你 马西墨斯
We'll wait here for you, Maximus.
- 勇气和荣誉 - 勇气和荣誉
- Strength and honor. - Strength and honor.
去吧
Go.
勇气和荣誉
Strength and honor.
瞄准 拉弓!
Aim. Arch your bows!
马可・奥勒留914-922
普罗西莫
一切终归尘土
Shadows and dust.
马西墨斯!
Maximus!
对不起
I'm sorry.
事情都解决了
It's done.
该如何处治我的外甥?
And what of my nephew?
还有他的母亲?
And what of his mother?
他们应该面对和她爱人相同的命运吗?
Should they share her lover's fate?
还是我应该网开一面?
Or should I be merciful?
仁慈的康莫德斯
Commodus the Merciful.
从现在起 卢修斯由我照顾
Lucius will stay with me now.
如果他母亲...
And if his mother
用令我不快的眼神看着我...
so much as looks at me
用令我不快的态度对我...
in a manner that displeases me,
他就会死
he will die.
如果她想...抵死不从...
If she decides to be noble,
或者想自杀的话...
and takes her own life,
他会死
he will die.
至于你...
And as for you,
你会爱我...
you will love me,
就像我爱你一样
as I have loved you.
你会帮我生育下一代 血统纯正的继承人...
You will provide me with an heir of pure blood,
那么康莫德斯
so that Commodus
和他的子孙...将世世代代统治罗马
and his progeny will rule for 1, 000 years.
我不够仁慈吗?
Am I not merciful?
Am I not merciful!
- 马西墨斯! 马西墨斯! 马西墨斯! - 马西墨斯! 马西墨斯! 马西墨斯!
- Maximus! Maximus! Maximus! - Maximus! Maximus! Maximus!
我是军人 我职责是服从
I'm a soldier. I obey.
没人可以逼你做你不愿意的事
Nothing happens to anyone that he is not fitted by nature to bear.
马西墨斯!
Maximus.
他们在为你欢呼
They call for you.
一个沦为奴隶的将军
The general who became a slave.
一个变成角斗士的奴隶
The slave who became a gladiator.
一个挑战皇帝的角斗士
The gladiator who defied an emperor.
一个震撼人心的故事
A striking story.
现在人们想知道故事的结局
Now the people want to know how the story ends.
只有一个出名的死亡才能令人满意
Only a famous death will do.
还有什么能比...
And what could be more glorious
在竞技场上亲自挑战皇帝来的光荣呢?
than to challenge the Emperor himself in the great arena?
- 你要和我决斗? - 为什么不?
- You would fight me? - Why not?
你以为我害怕吗?
Do you think I'm afraid?
我认为你一生人也在害怕
I think you have been afraid all your life.
不象无敌的马西墨斯 有谁从来不害怕?
Unlike Maximus the Invincible, who knows no fear?
一个我认识的人曾经说过 "死亡向所有人微笑...
I knew a man who once said, "Death smiles at us all.
人们所能做的就是还以微笑"
"All a man can do is smile back."
我在怀疑
I wonder,
你的朋友在面对死亡时也在微笑吗?
did your friend smile at his own death?
你要知道
You must know.
他是你父亲
He was your father.
我知道 你爱我的父亲
You loved my father, I know,
但我也爱他
but so did I.
我们因此是兄弟 不是吗?
That makes us brothers, doesn't it?
兄弟 对我微笑吧
Smile for me now, brother.
替他穿上盔甲 把伤口遮住
Strap on his armor. Conceal the wound.
成包围队形!
Ring formation!
昆塔斯 剑
Quintus, sword.
把你的剑给我!
Give me your sword.
剑! 给我把剑!
Sword! Give me a sword!
收剑入鞘! 收剑入鞘!
Sheathe your swords. Sheathe your swords!
马西墨斯
Maximus.
昆塔斯
Quintus.
还我的人自由
Free my men.
恢复格瑞克斯议员的职位
Senator Gracchus is to be reinstated.
罗马的共和是个梦想
There was a dream that was Rome.
它应当被实现
It shall be realized.
这些都是马可・奥勒留的心愿
These are the wishes of Marcus Aurelius.
释放囚犯 快去
Free the prisoners. Go!
马西墨斯
Maximus.
卢修斯安全了
Lucius is safe.
去找他们吧
Go to them.
你回到家了
You're home.
罗马值得一个好人牺牲性命吗?
Is Rome won'th one good mars life?
我们曾经相信
We believed it once.
那就让我们再次相信吧
Make us believe it again.
他是罗马的将士
He was a soldier of Rome.
让我们给他荣耀
Honor him.
谁愿意来帮我一起抬他?
Who will help me carry him?
现在我们都自由了
Now we are free.
我们会再见面的
I will see you again.
不过现在还不是时候
But not yet.
还不是时候
Not yet.